<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listApp xml:id="MP_listApp">
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p1">
               <note><ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35</ref> («Ci devise de la cité de
                     <placeName ref="#camandi">Comadi</placeName>»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35</ref> / <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr2.35">Fr2
                     35</ref> («Ci dit le .XXXV. chapitre d’une cité qui a non <placeName
                     ref="#camandi">Camady</placeName>» / «Ci dist d’une cité qui a non <placeName
                     ref="#camandi">Camadi</placeName>. .XXX.V.»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_L29">L 29</ref> («De civitate <placeName ref="#camandi"
                     >Camandi</placeName>»); <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22</ref>
                  («De civitate <placeName ref="#camandi">Camandu</placeName> et regione <placeName
                     ref="#reobar">Reobarle</placeName>. Capitulum 22»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TA35">TA 35</ref> («Di <placeName ref="#camandi"
                     >Camandi</placeName>»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TB36 #c35_TB37 #c35_TB38 #c35_TB39 #c35_TB40 #c35_TB41"
                     ><!-- verificare se il target così funziona o se bisogna "spezzettarlo" -->TB
                     36-TB 41</ref>; <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 8-24</ref> («Del
                  reame de <placeName ref="#crermain">Ereimain</placeName>»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 5-27</ref> («Della grande desexa et del pian dove è
                  grandisimi <term ref="#buef">boi</term> e <term ref="#monton">moltoni</term>»);
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 10-21</ref>; <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z13 #c35_Z14">Z 13; Z 14 20-30</ref><!-- idem qui se funziona -->.
                  The chapter is omitted in K. Chapter 35 is a chorographical description of the
                  great plain of <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>, which extends from
                     <placeName ref="#camandi">Qamadin</placeName> to the coast of <placeName
                     ref="#curmos">Hormuz</placeName>, in south-eastern Iran. First of all,
                     <persName ref="#marcoPolo">Marco Polo</persName> reviews its characteristic
                  flora and fauna; then he dedicates an ethno-historiographical digression to the
                     <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>, the marauder-magicians of Tartar origin
                  who passed through those lands, terrifying inhabitants (and whose rapacity the
                  Venetian himself had experienced), addressing the issue of their origins, which
                  was linked to the military exploits of the legendary king <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName>. Except for the usual fluctuation of variants and of the
                  tendency of some versions to summarise (especially L, P, TA) or to slightly rework
                  the content (VB), the redactions belonging to the α group and the Venetian
                  redaction V substantially present the same text in this chapter; the clearest
                  structural innovation is the complete omission of the historiographical digression
                  concerning <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_L29">L 29</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I
                     22</ref> and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA 35</ref>. Within the β
                  group, the Toledan manuscript (in which <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM
                     35</ref> is spread over two chapters: <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z13">Z
                     13</ref> and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 20-30</ref>) and
                  Ramusio’s “Milione” offer an extensively-reworked version of two sections of the
                  text, corresponding to <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 5-6</ref> (the
                  review of the typical fruits and birdlife in the <placeName ref="#reobar"
                     >Reobar</placeName> plain) and to <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35
                     11-19</ref> (the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ plundering techniques;
                  the historiographical digression concerning <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName>): concerning the first point, see <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z13">Z 13 3-6</ref> and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R
                     I 14 2-5</ref>, concerning the second, see <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 27-28</ref> – which, however, radically shortens it –
                  and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 9-13</ref>. Our translation
                  essentially follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35</ref>, with two
                  little ‘addenda’ (in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 2</ref> and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 5</ref>) drawn from the β group; the
                  two sections of the text reworked in Z and R have been translated on the basis of
                  these two redactions and placed at the end of the respective pericopes (<ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 3</ref> and <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 11</ref>), instead of being artificially merged with
                  the main text taken from F. </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p2">
               <note>Our translation follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 2-4</ref>
                  («Et quant l’en ha descendu celle deus <term ref="#journee">jorné</term> que je
                  voç ai dit, adonc treve une grandisme plaingne et ao començamant de cel plain a
                  une cité, qe est apelés <placeName ref="#camandi">Camandi</placeName>, que jadis
                  fu grant cité et noble a mervoille, mes orendroit ne est pas si grant ne si bone,
                  car <term ref="#tartars">Tartarç</term> d’autre païs la ont domajés plusor foies.
                  Et voç di qu’il est ‹en› celle plaingne mout chaut. Et la proense de coi nos
                  comi‹n›son hore est apellé <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>»), with the
                  addition of a chorographical datum – the extension of the <placeName ref="#reobar"
                     >Reobar</placeName> plain – drawn from the β group: it is to be found in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Z13">Z 13 1</ref> («invenitur quedam planicies
                  magna, que versus <term ref="#midi">meridiem</term> durat per .V. <term
                     ref="#journee">dietas</term> ») and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I
                     14 1</ref> («si trova una gran pianura, la qual verso <term ref="#midi"
                     >mezzodì</term> dura per cinque <term ref="#journee">giornate</term>»), but not
                  in <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 8</ref> («…el se trova una gran
                  pianura, et al chomenzamento de questa pianura»). As regards the rest of the
                  tradition of the text, the pericope is omitted in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 10-21</ref>, while in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_L29">L 29 1-2</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I
                     22 1-2</ref> and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z13">Z 13 1-3</ref> it is
                  summarised and all the other redactions closely follow the Franco-Italian one.
                  Finally, it is interesting to point out that F shares with L and TA an error of
                  clear paleographic origin (-t > -e): in the text of the Parisian manuscript, the
                  noun «plaingne», ‘plain’, is accompanied by the adjective «chave», ‘hollow,
                  depressed’ (written «chaue» in the manuscript), appropriately corrected to
                  «chaut», ‘hot’, by the editors of F, on the basis of the stemma (cf. <ref
                     type="bibli" target="#eusebi_burgio_2018">Eusebi, Burgio 2018, 1: 59</ref>);
                  earlier Franco-Italian manuscripts that had the same variant as F (‹chaue›), or a
                  very similar one, generated the texts of <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L
                     29 1</ref> («[planicies] est valde concava et depressa») and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 3</ref> («Questo piano è molto cavo»).
               </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p3">
               <note>Our translation of the description of the flora and fauna in the <placeName
                     ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName> plain closely follows <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_F35">F 35 5-6</ref> («Les sien fruit sunt datarlet <term
                     ref="#pomeParais">pome de paraïse</term> et <term ref="#pistac">pistac</term>
                  et autres fruit les quelz ne sunt en nostre leu froit. Et en ceste plaingn a une
                  generasion d’oisiaus que l’en apelle <term ref="#francolin">francolin</term>, que
                  sunt devissé a les autres <term ref="#francolin">francolin</term> des autres païs,
                  car il sunt noir et blance mesleemant, et les piés et les bech{o} ont rouges.»),
                  except for the adjective ‘many’ in the phrase «many other fruits», absent in the
                  Franco-Italian redaction, but unanimously confirmed by the rest of the tradition:
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L 29 3</ref> («alii quam plures
                  fructus»), <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 4</ref> («autrs fruis
                  assez») and <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 10</ref> («molti altri
                  fruti»), etc. As regards the ‘varia lectio’, we notice, in addition to the
                  omission of the entire pericope in <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22
                     10-21</ref>, the usual tendency to abridge shown by <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 4</ref> («suoi frutti sono <term ref="#dattal"
                     >dattari</term>, <term ref="#pistac">pistacchi</term>, <term ref="#pomeParais"
                     >frutti di paradiso</term> e altri frutti che non son di qua»), removing the
                  description of the <term ref="#francolin">francolins</term> and by Friar Pipino in
                  his redaction, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22 3-4</ref> («Ibi sunt
                     <term ref="#dattal">dactili</term>, <term ref="#pistac">pistachi</term> et
                     <term ref="#pomeParais">poma Paradisi</term> in copia maxima, multique fructus
                  alii crescunt ibi qui apud nos habentur. Ibi sunt aves qui dicuntur ‘<term
                     ref="#francolin">francolini</term>’, coloris permixti albi et nigri; rubei
                  autem coloris habent pedes et rostra») ; the latter contains a singular error,
                  perhaps due to a “saut du même au même” (‘nos habentur’ > *‘nos non [or ‘nos nō’]
                  habentur’ ?), which overturns the meaning of the text. Finally, for a discussion
                  about the errors in <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 10-11</ref> («Et li
                  suo’ fruti sono <term ref="#dattal">datali</term> e <term ref="#pomeParais">pome
                     del paradixo</term> et sono molti altri fruti li quali non se trova in ’ste
                  parte per el gran fredo. Et in questa pianura se trova una zenerazion de oxeli li
                  quali sono chiamati <term ref="#francolin">francholini</term>, ch’è simele ali
                     <term ref="#fauchon">falchoni</term> dele altre parte, et sì è negri e bianchi
                  mesedadi ed à el becho negro») see <ref type="bibl" target="#simion_2019">Simion
                     2019, 392</ref>. In Z and R we can read an alternative version of the first
                  part of the pericope, containing more information about the flora and fauna of
                     <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName> compared to the rest of the
                  tradition: cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z13">Z 13 3-6</ref> («producit
                  frumentum et alia blada. Nascuntur poma granata, citrana et multi alii fructus et
                  poma, que in nostris partibus frigidis non nascuntur. Conversantur ibi turtures
                  infiniti, propter multas pomelas quas ibi inveniunt ad edendum; et sunt sine
                  numero, nec <term ref="#saracinz">saraceni</term> de eis comedunt unquam, quia eos
                  aborrent. Inveniuntur et ibi <term ref="#faicain">fassiani</term>, <term
                     ref="#francolin">franculini</term> et alie aves multe») and <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 2-5</ref> («et produce formento, orzo et altre
                  biade. Per le coste delli monti di detta pianura nascono pomi granati, codogni et
                  molti altri frutti, et <term ref="#pomeParais">pomi di Adamo</term>, i quali nelle
                  nostre parti fredde non nascono. Ivi sono infinite tortore, per le molte pomelle
                  che vi trovano da mangiare, né li <term ref="#saracinz">Saraceni</term> mai le
                  pigliano, perché le hanno in abominatione. Vi si trovano anchora molti <term
                     ref="#faicain">fagiani</term> et <term ref="#francolin">francholini</term>, li
                  quali non si assimigliano»). For its part, the Toledan manuscript also shows the
                  same textual variant witnessed by the α group and V, but it is placed - together
                  with the rest of the digression on <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>’s
                     <term ref="#buef">oxen</term>, <term ref="#monton">rams</term> and marauders -
                  in the following chapter, after the passage where <persName ref="#marcoPolo">Marco
                     Polo</persName> describes his return journey from <placeName ref="#curmos"
                     >Hormuz</placeName> to <placeName ref="#crermain">Kerman</placeName>: cf. <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 20-22</ref> («Hic est quidem contrata pro
                  maiori parte fructuum. Sunt <term ref="#dattal">dactuli</term> et <term
                     ref="#pomeParais">poma paradisi</term> et alie maneries fructuum quam plures,
                  qui in nostris locis frigidis non nascuntur. Et ibi quoddam genus avium nomine
                     <term ref="#francolin">franculini</term>, qui a <term ref="#francolin"
                     >franculinis</term> aliarum contractarum disimilant»). As regards this
                  particular textual and structural misalignment between the Toledan text and the
                  rest of the tradition, see <ref type="bibl" target="#mascherpa_2008">Mascherpa
                     2008, 176-8</ref>.</note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p4">
               <note>Our translation closely follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35
                     7-8</ref> («Les bestes sunt aussi divisee, et voç dirai des <term ref="#buef"
                     >bué</term> primeramant. Les <term ref="#buef">buef</term> sunt grandismes et
                  sunt tuit blance come nois; le poi‹l› il ont peitet et |16a| plain, et ce avient
                  por le caut leu; il ont les cornes cortes et groses et non agues; entre les
                  spaules ont un çinb reont haut bien deus paumes: il sunt la plus belle chause dou
                  monde a veoir. Et quant l’en le vuelt chargier, il se coucent ausint con font les
                     <term ref="#giamiaus">giamiaius</term>; et quant l’en le a chargés, il se
                  levent et portent lor chargies mout bien, car il sunt forte outre meçure»), whose
                  text is substantially confirmed by the tradition, excluding any little differences
                  between the redactions. Thus, in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22
                     5</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 10-11</ref> and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 23-25</ref> we observe the usual tendency
                  to summarise, while TB shows the evident error of attributing to the yaks some
                  physical features of the rams, which are described immediately afterwards (<ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TB37">TB 37 4</ref> «e quando e’ sono charichati si
                  levano e portano molto bene lo peso loro, ché sono forti chome asini e ànno la
                  choda sì grossa e sì llargha {p} che pesa ben trenta libre; e’ sono molto belli e
                  molto grassi è sono buoni da mangiare»); VA overturns the meaning of the note
                  about yaks’ horns, replacing ‘non’ with ‘sono’ (error due maybe to a bad reading:
                  ‘non’ > *‘son’: VA 22 10 «le chorne churte e grosse et sono achute»); finally, V
                  compromises the meaning of two points of the pericope, by inserting first the
                  adjective ‘similar’ where the whole tradition contains its antonym (cf. F
                  ‘divisee’, Fr ‘devisees’, etc.), then the noun ‘onge’, ‘nails’, where F has
                  ‘agues’, Fr ‘aguës’, ‘pointed’, etc. (maybe a Franco-Italian syntagm *‘non augue’
                  has been improperly segmented: *‘non augue’ > * ‘non au[n]gue’ > ‘nonn à onge’):
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 12-13</ref> «Et le altre bestie è
                  simele ale nostre. Li <term ref="#buef">buò</term> sono molti grandi e tuti
                  bianchi chomo neve, ed à uno pelo pizolo e baso e questo sono per el chaldo
                  grando; ed à le chorne churte e grosse et nonn à onge, et ale spalle à uno gobo
                  groso do palma; al veder someiâ <term ref="#giamiaus">ganbeli</term>, e queli vien
                  chargadi et metese zoxo e poi se lieva chomo fano i <term ref="#giamiaus"
                     >ganbeli</term>, et porta chargo oltra muodo perché i sono forti» (see <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#simion_2019">Simion 2019, 392</ref>).</note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p5">
               <note>Our translation substantially follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F
                     35 9</ref> («Il ha <term ref="#monton">mouton</term> grant com <term
                     ref="#asnes">asne</term>; et ont la coe si grosse et si large que bien poisse
                  trente livres; il sunt mout biaus et gras et sunt buen a manger»), with the
                  addition of a little specification about the weight of the rams’ tail – «and even
                  more» – drawn from the redactions of the β group: cf. <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 26</ref> («Sunt etiam ibi <term ref="#monton"
                     >arietes</term> magnitudinis <term ref="#asnes">asinorum</term>, qui sunt grosi
                  et largi caudas ita quod una est bene ponderis .XXX. librarum et plurium»), <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 7</ref> («Vi sono anchora <term
                     ref="#monton">castroni</term> di grandezza de <term ref="#asnes">asini</term>,
                  che hanno le code grosse et larghe, di sorte che una pesarà libbre trenta et piú,
                  et sono grassi et buoni da mangiare»), and <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V
                     20 14</ref> («Anchora se trova <term ref="#monton">chastroni</term> grandi
                  chomo <term ref="#asnes">axeni</term>, li quali àno la choda tanto grasa che pexa
                  più de trenta livre grosse ed è molti boni da manzar»). As for the rest of the
                  versions, we notice flawed variants in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA
                     35 7</ref>, where the erroneous syntagm «<term ref="#monton">montoni</term>
                  [...] bia‹n›chi» may be due to a misreading of the Franco-Italian adjective:
                  «biaus» > *bians, and in <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 12</ref>,
                  which attributes to the yaks some features that <persName ref="#marcoPolo">Marco
                     Polo</persName> assigns instead to the rams («Ànno la choda grossisima – chome
                  ànno i <term ref="#monton">chastroni</term> di <placeName ref="#tartaria"
                     >Tartaria</placeName> – et, al mio iudicio, di pexo de libre .XXX. e bonissima
                  da mangiare»; the same error is to be found in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TB37">TB 37 4</ref>: see our commentary to <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 4</ref>). </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p6">
               <note>Here the digression about the ethnic group of the <term ref="#caraunas"
                     >Qara’unas</term> begins (see <ref type="bibl" target="#simion_burgio_2015"
                     >Simion, Burgio 2015, s.v. «Caraunas»</ref>): our translation closely follows
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 10-11</ref> («En ceste plaingne a
                  plusor castiaus et viles que unt les mur de tere hautes et groses por defendre{s}
                  elç des <term ref="#caraunas">Caraunas</term>, ce sunt berovierç que vont corant
                  les païs. Et por coi s’apellent <term ref="#caraunas">caraonas</term>? Po‹r› ce ke
                  lor mere sunt esté indiene et lor pere tartarç»); <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_L29">L 29 8</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TB38">TB 38
                     1-2</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 15-16</ref> and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 13-14</ref>. Some redactions summarise
                  this pericope: <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22 7</ref> removes the
                  note on the origin of the name ‘<term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ («In hac
                  planice multe sunt civitates et oppida, et habent muros luteos grossos valde et
                  fortes, quia in regione illa multi predones sunt, qui dicuntur ‘<term
                     ref="#caraunas">caraonas</term>’»), while <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 8</ref> («In questo piano à castella e città e ville
                  murate di terra per difender‹si› da scherani che vanno ro‹b›ando») even omits the
                  name, unless the noun ‘scherani’ is a ‘facilior’ lexical variant of ‘<term
                     ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ (cf. <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#pelliot_1959-1973">Pelliot 1959-1973, 1: 183</ref>). In the
                  MiddleFrench redaction, the close double occurrence of the ethnonym produces an
                  error: cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 13-15</ref> («En ce
                  plain a pluisours chastiaus et viles qui ont lors murs de terre haut et gros a
                  deffendre soi des <term ref="#tartars">Tartars</term> [Fr2 Carriax] qui y sont
                  assez, et les apelent <term ref="#caraunas">Caraonas</term>. Pour quoi ont il ce
                  non? Pour ce que leur meres sont indiennes et leur peres <term ref="#tartars"
                     >tartars</term>»). As regards VB, the author of the redaction misunderstands
                  the meaning of the passage: indeed, he attributes the name ‘<term ref="#caraunas"
                     >Caraor</term>’ – and, consequently, the bad habits of that people listed in
                  the following lines – to the inhabitants of the plain themselves, instead of to
                  the bands of marauders (<ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 13</ref> «In
                  questo piano v’è molte forteçe: àno i llor muri di terra per difexa loro; e
                  chiamasi questa çente <term ref="#caraunas">Caraor</term>, che tanto vene a dire
                  chome in nostra lengua <term ref="#guasmul">gasmulli</term> over bastardi, però
                  che antigamente i sono desesi per madre de dona d’<placeName ref="#ynde"
                     >India</placeName> e per padre <term ref="#tartars">tartaro</term>»). It is
                  interesting to note that the author of VB employs the noun «<term ref="#guasmul"
                     >gasmulli</term>», ‘half-blood’, to better define the crossbreeding of the
                     <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>: this is a term of Greek-Byzantine
                  origin which entered the vocabulary of Old French (cf. <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#andreose_2017">Andreose 2017</ref>, 34, with bibliography) and which
                  occurs only once and much further on in the other redactions, i.e. in the chapter
                  dedicated to the province of <placeName ref="#tenducProvincia">Tenduc</placeName>
                     (<ref type="witlink" target="#c73_F73">F 73 13</ref>), as a French/Romance?
                  translation of the Turkish word «<term ref="#argon2">argon</term>», ‘mixed-blood’
                     (<ref type="bibl" target="#pelliot_1959-1973">Pelliot 1959-1973, 1: 48-9</ref>;
                     <ref type="bibl" target="#simion_burgio_2015">Simion, Burgio 2015, s.v.
                     «argon»</ref>). Finally, as regards Ramusio’s version (<ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 8-9</ref> «In questa provincia vi sono molti
                  castelli et città che hanno le mura di terra alte et grosse, et questo per potersi
                  difendere dalli <term ref="#caraunas">Caraunas</term>, che vanno scorrendo per
                  tutti quelli luoghi depredando il tutto. Et acciò che si sappi quello che vuol
                  dire questo nome di <term ref="#caraunas">Caraunas</term>, dico che fu uno
                     <persName ref="#nogodar">Nugodar</persName>»), it is very close to F at least
                  up to the question of the ethnonym: from that point on, and until <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 13</ref>, R presents the digression
                  about the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term> and <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> in a reworked version, partially confirmed by the Toledan
                  manuscript, which is unfortunately very incomplete here cf. <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 27-28</ref>).</note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p7">
               <note>Our translation exactly follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35
                     12</ref> («Et cest gens quant il vuelent corer les païs et rober, il font por
                  lor encantemant, pour evre diablotique, tout le jor devenir oscur, si que l’en ne
                  voit loingne se pou non, e ceste oscurité font durer .VII. <term ref="#journee"
                     >jornee</term> a lonc»), to which <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L 29
                     8</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TB39">TB 39 1</ref>, <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 17</ref>, <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 15</ref> roughly correspond. In Friar Pipino’s
                  redaction, which belongs to the VA group, the ‘singularis’ detail about the
                  extension of darkness «in magno spacio» (<ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P
                     I 22 7</ref>) perhaps derives from an interpretation of the adverbial phrase
                  «da lonzi» (or similar) occurring in the source text (see VA 22 15 «egli fano, per
                  inchantamento e per opera de diavoli, che ’l tenpo chiaro se oschurisse sì chome
                  el fosse de note, sì che l’omo non pò vedere da lonzi se non pocho»). VB abridges
                  and reworks the text (cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 14</ref> «È
                  mallissima e prava çeneracione de robatori e negromanti: intanto quando volle
                  andar a robar, i fano oschurar el solle et, oschurato, non se vedendo quaxi
                  lume»). In the β group, the alternative version of Z and R describe the visual
                  effects of magical darkness in a slightly different – and more concrete – way
                  (i.e. «if you are not close to your companion, it is impossible for you to see
                  him»): see <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 27</ref> («Istis partibus
                  inveniuntur aliqui qui sciunt artes magicas et dyabolicas, quibus tota die
                  celebrant [sic for ‘tenebrant’] et obscurant ita quod, nisi unus sit prope alium,
                  videri non posunt») and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 12</ref>
                  («Et come vennero in <placeName ref="#melibar">Malabar</placeName> imparorono
                  l’arti magice et diabolice, con le quali sanno far venir tenebre et oscurar il
                  giorno, di modo che, se uno non è appresso a l’altro, non si veggono»). A similar
                  variant also occurs, maybe for polygenesis, also in the α group, in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 16</ref> («si font […] tout le jour
                  devenir oscur, que a paines voit on son compaignon pres de lui») and in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 9</ref> («E questa gente che corre lo
                  paese, per incantamento fanno parere notte VII <term ref="#journee"
                     >giornate</term> a la lunga, perché altri non si possa guardare»), which, as
                  usual, summarises the text.</note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p8">
               <note>Our translation follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 13-14</ref>
                  literally («Il sevent mout bien les païs. Il chevauchent, quant il ont faite la
                  scurité, le un dejoste l’autre; et sunt bien .Xm. tel fois, et tel fois plus, et
                  telz foiz moin, si qu’il prennent tout le plan dont il vuelent rober, si que tuit
                  celz que il trovent en les plennes ne poent excanper, ne homes ne bestes ne
                  couses, qu’il n’estoient prises. Et puis qu’il ont pris les homes, il occient tuit
                  les velz, et les jeunes enmoinent et les vendent pour sers et pour esclaif»);
                  substantially the same text can be read in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 17-19</ref> («Il sevent moult bien le païs et
                  chevauchent l’un pres de l’autre et sont aucune foiz .X. <term ref="#mil"
                     >mile</term>, tel foiz plus ou mains, si que il prendent tout le plain. Et touz
                  ceuz qu’il truvent em plain hors de vile ou [de] chastel sont pris, qu’il n’en
                  puet eschaper ne homme ne femme ne bestail. Et puis qu’il ont pris tout, il
                  occient les hommes viellars, et les jones et les femmes vendent par autres païs
                  pour esclas, si que il destruient moult la contree et l’ont presque toute
                  deserté»), with the insertion of two redundant and ‘singulares’ textual segments
                  which are surely not original («em plain […] chastel», «si que il destruient […]
                  deserté»). As regards the VA family, it has two characteristic variants: an
                  erroneous translation («passi» &gt; Franco-Italian «païs») and a sort of
                  explanatory gloss about the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ plundering
                  technique: cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 16-18</ref> («E sano
                  molto ben i pasi: e loro chavalchano uno a pe’ del’altro; e sono alle fiate ben
                  Xm, sì che i fano sì longa schiera ch’el non pò passar niuno che non sia prexo,
                  perché ’li prendeno chotanto tereno che niuno non pò schanpar per quel piano.
                  Quando i fano questa cotal chavalchata, e prendeno homeni e bestie. E quando i àno
                  prexi li homeni, egli alzideno i vechi, e i gioveni vendeno per schiavi») and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TB39">TB 39 2-3</ref> («Eglino sanno molto bene gli
                  passi è cavalchano tutti l’uno a piè dell’altro e sono talvolta ben xm, sì che
                  fanno sì lungha schiera e pigliano tanto terreno che niuno può passare che non sia
                  preso. Per quel piano quando egli fanno cotale chavalchata pigliano huomini e
                  bestie e quando egli ànno presi gli uomini eglino uccidono tutti li vechi e i
                  giovani vendono per schiavi»); this gloss is also to be found in Friar Pipino’s
                  abridged redaction: <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22 7</ref> «et
                  tunc predones illi egredientes ad campos, quandoque numero decem milia, ordinant
                  se per longas acies unus pariter iuxta alium in latitudine magna, ita ut rarus sit
                  inde pertransiens qui non incidat manus eorum: capiunt autem homines et iumenta,
                  vendunt iuvenes et senes occidunt». As usual, the L and TA redactions abbreviate
                  their source texts (<ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L 29 8</ref> «Et tunc
                  ipsi, qui bene noverunt contratam, incedunt simul aliquando bene .Xm., et capiunt
                  animalia et homines et quecumque volunt; verum quod omnes senes occidunt; iuvenes
                  verum conservant, pro servis vendunt»; <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA
                     35 9-10</ref> «quando ànno fatto questo, vanno per lo paese, ché bene lo sanno.
                  E’ son bene Xm, talvolta più e meno, sicché per quello piano no li scampa né uomo
                  né bestia: li vecchi ucidono, gli giovani ménagli a vendere per ischiavi»), while
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 14</ref> summarises and slightly
                  reworks («et, oschurato, non se vedendo quaxi lume, essendo loro avixati d’i
                  paexi, entrano nei chaxali e vile e robano; et quanta giente trovano pigliano, e
                  vechi sença nulla piatà tuti alcideno, i çoveni vendeno»: cf. our commentary to
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 7</ref>). Within the β group, the
                  text of <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 18</ref> («Et fato questo i
                  vano per quela pianura chavalchando l’uno apreso l’altro, molti in chonpagnia, e
                  partese in molte parte; et per questo modo lor tien tuta la pianura, et tuti queli
                  ch’eli trova vieno prexi et nesun, homo nì animal, non li può schanpare; et quando
                  i prende algun omo vechio i lo alzide, e li zoveni vende») is very close to the
                  Franco-Italian one, except for a ‘lectio singularis’ («molti in chonpagnia, e
                  partese in molte parte»), which is perhaps a paraphrase of <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_F35">F 35 13</ref> («et sunt bien .Xm. tel fois, et tel fois plus,
                  et telz foiz moin»). As regards R and Z on the other hand, they provide a richer
                  and deeply reworked version of the description of the <term ref="#caraunas"
                     >Qara’unas</term>’ raids: cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14
                     13</ref> («Et cavalcano il piú delle volte verso le parti di <placeName
                     ref="#reobar">Reobarle</placeName>, perciò che tutti i mercatanti che vengono a
                  negociar in <placeName ref="#curmos">Ormus</placeName>, fin che si avisano che
                  venghino i mercatanti dalle parti d’<placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>,
                  mandano al tempo del verno i <term ref="#mul">muli</term> et <term ref="#giamiaus"
                     >camelli</term>, che si son smagrati per la lunghezza del cammino, alla pianura
                  di <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobarle</placeName>, dove per l’abondanza dell’herbe
                  debbano ingrassarsi: et questi <term ref="#caraunas">Caraunas</term>, che
                  attendono a questo, vanno depredando ogni cosa, et prendono gl’huomini et
                  vendongli; nondimeno se possono riscattarsi li lasciano andar») and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 28</ref> («Et sic quandoque equitant per
                  .XXX. et .XL. <term ref="#journee">dietas</term>, et ut plurimum versus partes
                     <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>, et capiunt homines ipsosque
                  vendunt»). Unfortunately, the Toledan manuscript shows a radically abridged text
                  here, while the Z manuscript that Ramusio used for his translation was
                  substantially complete. </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p9">
               <note>Our translation follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 15</ref>
                  exactly («Le{s} lor roi est apellés <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName>. E
                  cestui <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> ala ‹a la› cort de <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Ciagati</persName>, qui estoit frere charnaus au <term
                     ref="#grantKaan">Grant Can</term>, bien cun .Xm. homes de sa jens, et demoroit
                  o lui por ce que sen oncle estoit et mout grant sire; et atant qu’il demoroit ho
                  lui, <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> se pense et fist grant felonie, e
                  voç dirai comant»), preserving both the note that presents <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName> as a ‘great sovereign’ («et mout grant
                  sire»), and the narrative transition that closes the pericope («et atant [...]
                  comant»). Although these two textual segments probably belonged to the original
                  text, many redactions abridge or delete them, in accordance with a marked trend to
                  simplify the long historiographical digression about king <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> (<ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L 29</ref>, <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22</ref> and <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 20-30</ref> even omit it, while <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 11</ref> reduces it to only one line: «Lo loro re à
                  nome <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName>, e sono gente rea e malvage e
                  crudele»). In addition to F, the note about ‘the (great) sovereign <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName>’ can be found in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TB40">TB 40 1</ref> («Questo <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Negodar</persName> andò a la corte di <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Ciagati</persName>, ch’era fratello del <term ref="#grantKaan">Gran
                     Chaam</term>, e andò bene chome diecie miglia huomini di su’ gente, e stette un
                  tempo in sua corte perch’egli era suo sio ed era troppo gran Signore») and in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 15</ref> («Era segnor di questa giente
                     <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogador</persName>, homo de grandissimo animo, el
                  qualle, raunatto .Xm. d’i suo’ crudelisimi et animosi homeni, deliberò andare a
                  vixitar <persName ref="#ciagatai">Gragatin</persName>, el qual era suo parente e
                  fratello del <term ref="#grantKaan">Gran Chan</term>, segnor de una nobelle
                  provincia»). In the β group we find it in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14"
                     >R I 14 9</ref> («Et acciò che si sappi quello che vuol dire questo nome di
                     <term ref="#caraunas">Caraunas</term>, dico che fu uno <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nugodar</persName>, nepote di <persName ref="#ciagatai">Zagathai</persName>,
                  fratello del <term ref="#grantKaan">Gran Can</term>, qual <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Zagathai</persName> signoreggiava la <placeName
                     ref="#grantTurquie">Turchia Maggiore</placeName>»; here, the omission of the
                  reference to the 10,000 soldiers escorting <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> is part of the overall reworking of the digression: see our
                  commentary to <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 10</ref>). The
                  narrative transition, on the other hand, appears in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 22</ref>, in a form identical to the Franco-Italian
                  one («Et demourant o lui, s’apensa celui <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogadar</persName> une grant felonnie et vous dirai comment») and, within the
                  β group, in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 10</ref> («Questo
                     <persName ref="#nogodar">Nugodar</persName>, stando nella sua corte, si pensò
                  di voler anchor lui signoreggiar, et però» [&lt; Z?]), while all other redactions
                  generally reduce it to its first part only: see <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 21</ref> («E stete uno tenpo in sua chorte e po’ se
                  partì»), <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 16</ref> («E demorado con
                  lui per algun tenpo, adoperò per modo ch’el desvià .Xm. omeni d’arme») and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 19-21</ref> («Lo re de questi vien
                  chiamado <persName ref="#nogodar">Negodar</persName>. Et questo una volta andò ala
                  chorte de <persName ref="#ciagatai">Agati</persName>, fradelo del <term
                     ref="#grantKaan">Gran Chan</term>, chon diexemilia omeni dela so zente, et
                  stete chon elo perché lui era so barba. Et stando questo <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Negodar</persName> chon questo suo barba, uno zorno questo se partì»). </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p10">
               <note>Our translation follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 16</ref>
                  exactly («Il se parti da son uncle <persName ref="#ciagatai">Ciagatai</persName>,
                  ke en la <placeName ref="#grandeArminie">Grant Arminie</placeName> estoit, et
                  s’enfui bien cun .Xm. de se gens, qe mout estoient cruelz et fellonç, et s’en
                  passe por <placeName ref="#badascian">Badasian</placeName>et por une provence que
                  s’apelle <placeName ref="#pasciai">Pasciai</placeName> et por un’autre provence
                  ‹que› a a nom <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chesciemur</placeName>, et el l’an perdi
                  maintes des ses jens et de ses bestes, por ce ke les voies estoient estroites et
                  mauveises») and the Middle-French text is very close to it (<ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 23</ref> «Il se parti de son oncle, qui en la
                     <placeName ref="#GrandeArmenie">Grant Ermenie</placeName> estoit, et s’en afuy
                  avec une quantité de gent a <term ref="#chevauz">cheval</term>, qui moult estoient
                  cruel, et s’en passa parmi <placeName ref="#badascian">Badasiam</placeName> et par
                  une autre prouvence qui s’apelle <placeName ref="#pasciai">Pallay</placeName> et
                  par une autre qui [a a non] <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chesiemar</placeName>, et
                  iluec perdi maintes de ses gens et de ses bestes, pour ce que les voies sont
                  estroites et mauvaises»), except for two details: 1. the detailed (and
                  ‘singularis’) specification about the troops who flee with <persName
                     ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName>, described in Fr as «gent a <term
                     ref="#chevauz">cheval</term>» (in the Middle-French redaction the same peculiar
                  ‘addendum’ also characterises, just above, the description of the soldiers that
                  had accompanied <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> to <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName>’s court: <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 21</ref> «avec lui bien .X.M. hommes a <term
                     ref="#chevauz">cheval</term> de sa gent»); 2. the omission of the exact number
                  of soldiers and of the possessive adjective relating to them (Fr «s’en afuy avec
                  une quantité de gent a <term ref="#chevauz">cheval</term>» vs F «Il se parti […]
                  cun .Xm. de se gens»); maybe this is an attempt to resolve the ambiguity of this
                  passage. This ambiguity – which probably goes back to the archetype – derives on
                  the one hand from the repetition, within a few lines, of the number ‘10,000’
                  referring to Nogodar’s soldiers: according to F and other redactions, <persName
                     ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> reaches <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Chaghadai</persName>’s court with 10,000 men (see our commentary to <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_tr35">DM 35 9</ref>) and leaves it with just as
                  many (as regards the close relationship, in the <hi rend="italic">Devisement dou
                     monde</hi>, between the number ‘10,000’ and the <term ref="#caraunas"
                     >Qara’unas</term>, see <ref type="bibl" target="#yule_cordier_1929"
                     >Yule-Cordier 1929, 1: 101</ref>). On the other, it stems from the ambivalence
                  of the possessive adjective in the Franco-Italian text («se gens» whose?). In
                  other words, who exactly are the ten thousand men with whom <persName
                     ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> flees from his uncle’s court? Are they the
                  same ones with whom he had arrived, or are they <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Chaghadai</persName>’s soldiers which <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> ‘steals’ from him? The tricky nature of the text in this
                  passage has led to different solutions being adopted in the tradition of the text.
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 21</ref> is very close to F («Et
                  stando questo <persName ref="#nogodar">Negodar</persName> chon questo suo barba,
                  uno zorno questo se partì da ‘sto so barba <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Agati</persName> chon diexemilia homeni dela so zente quali erano molto
                  chrudelissimi»), while <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 21-22</ref>
                  omits both the number and the possessive, as does Fr («E stete uno tenpo in sua
                  chorte e po’ se partì della chorte de <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Chiagati</persName> chon gran zente, e quella zente che andò con lui era
                  chrudelisimi e felloni», but see below the variant of TB). Some redactions instead
                  explicitly refer to the ‘theft of troops’ committed by <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> against his uncle: this is so in <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_TB40">TB 40 2</ref> («E quando egli fu stato nella corte di
                     <persName ref="#ciagatai">Cugati</persName>, egli se n’andò con gran gente di
                  quel re, lo quale era gito in <placeName ref="#GrandeArmenie">Erminia
                     magiore</placeName>, e quegli che andaro chò llui erano huomini crudelissemi e
                  felloni»), <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 16</ref> («E demorado con
                  lui per algun tenpo, adoperò per modo ch’el desvià .Xm. omeni d’arme dela più
                  fiorita brigata avese <persName ref="#ciagatai">Gragatin</persName> suo parente,
                  et con questi .XXm. valorosi et audaci omeni se ne fuçì»; here, the mathematical
                  sum of the two armies underlines the redactor’s interpretation) and finally in
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 10</ref> («et però, sentendo che
                     nell’<placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName> vi era una provincia chiamata
                     <placeName ref="#melibar">Malabar</placeName>, sotto ad un re nominato
                     <persName ref="#asidinSoldam">Asidin</persName>
                  <term ref="#soldan">soldano</term>, la qual non era soggiogata al dominio de’
                     <term ref="#tartars">Tartari</term>, sottrasse circa diecimila huomini, di
                  quelli ch’egli pensava esser peggiori et piú crudeli»). In Ramusio’s redaction,
                  this pericope should be noted for some characteristic variants: 1. an ‘addendum’
                  in which the reasons that encouraged <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName>
                  to invade <placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName> are clearly explained
                  («sentendo che nell’<placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName> vi era una provincia
                  chiamata <placeName ref="#melibar">Malabar</placeName>, sotto ad un re nominato
                     <persName ref="#asidinSoldam">Asidin</persName>
                  <term ref="#soldan">soldano</term>, la qual non era soggiogata al dominio de’
                     <term ref="#tartars">Tartari</term>»; for the question of the toponym
                     <placeName ref="#melibar">Malabar</placeName> [R] vs <placeName ref="#dilivar"
                     >Dilivar</placeName> and its variants in all other redactions, cf. <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#yule_cordier_1929">Yule-Cordier 1929, 1: 104-5</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#pelliot_1959-1973">Pelliot 1959-1973, 626</ref>; <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#mascherpa_2015">Mascherpa 2015, commentary to the
                     pericope</ref>); 2. a short textual insertion aimed at highlighting the secrecy
                  of <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName>’s escape («et con questi partendosi
                  da suo barba <persName ref="#ciagatai">Zagathai</persName> senza fargli intender
                  cosa alcuna, passò per Balaxan»); 3. the omission of Pashai from the list of
                  regions the rebel prince passed through (in F and in the whole α group we find
                     <placeName ref="#badascian">Badakhshan</placeName>, <placeName ref="#pasciai"
                     >Pashai</placeName> and <placeName ref="#kesimur">Kashmir</placeName>, while in
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 10</ref> we read «senza fargli
                  intender cosa alcuna, passò per <placeName ref="#badascian">Balaxan</placeName> et
                  per certa provincia chiamata <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chesmur</placeName>, dove
                  perse molte delle sue genti»). The last two variants are also to be found in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 22</ref> («Senza alguna providenzia pasò
                  per <placeName ref="#badascian">Sobasain</placeName>, per la provinzia de
                     <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chisuamor</placeName>, et prese – error for ‘perse’ –
                  molta zente e animali»): see the commentary to the pericope in <ref type="bibl"
                     target="#simion_2019">Simion 2019, 392-3</ref>. In the Toledan manuscript these
                  lines are missing. Finally, it is interesting to note that, within the α group,
                  the Fr and VA families – which are not close to each other in the ‘stemma codicum’
                  – share an error in the writing of the toponym <placeName ref="#kesimur"
                     >Kashmir</placeName>: cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35
                     23</ref> («qui a non <placeName ref="#kesimur">Aarion Chesiemar</placeName>»),
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr2.35">Fr2 35 21</ref> («qui a non <placeName
                     ref="#kesimur">Ariora Chiesiema</placeName>»), <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 22</ref> («per ‹una› che è apellata
                  Arionichisorennor») and <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TB40">TB 40 3</ref> («per
                  una ch’à nome <placeName ref="#kesimur">Aaron Chesiemur</placeName>»), etc. These
                  deviations from the correct form of the toponym probably occurred in the
                  Franco-Italian subarchetype of the α group, and clearly depend on a dittography
                  (*‘a a nom a a nom <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chesciemur</placeName>’ > ‘à a non
                     <placeName ref="#kesimur">Ariora Chiesiema</placeName>’, etc.: cf. <ref
                     type="bibl" target="#pelliot_1959-1973">Pelliot 1959-1973, 1: 242</ref>). The
                  fact that some witnesses of Fr family show the correct text (<ref type="bibl"
                     target="#menard_2001-2009">Ménard 2001-2009, I, 250</ref>) suggests that it was
                  not difficult, for some copyists, to correct the error. </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p11">
               <note>Our translation follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 17-19</ref>
                  («Et quant il unt toutes cestes provences passé, il entrent en <placeName
                     ref="#ynde">Yndie</placeName>, en lo confin a une provence qui est apellés
                     <placeName ref="#dilivar">Dilivar</placeName>; il pristent une noble cité que a
                  a nom <placeName ref="#diliDilivar">Dili Dilivar</placeName>. Et demore en cele
                  cité et pri le |16c| regne qu’il colli a un roi, que avoit a nom <persName
                     ref="#asidinSoldan">Asidin Soldan</persName>, que mout estoit grant et riche.
                  Et iluec demore <persName ref="#nogodar">Nugodar</persName> cun seç jens, et no a
                  doutre de nelui; il fait ghere a tous les autres <term ref="#tartars"
                     >Tartarç</term> que environ son reingne demorent») except for the textual
                  segment «et pri [‘conquered’? ms. ‘pro’] le regne», to which we have preferred the
                  variant with the prepositional phrase of place which is found in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 24</ref> («et demoura en cele cité
                  et par celui regne») and in the VA family (cf. <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 24</ref> «demorà in quella zità per lo regniame» and
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TB40">TB 40 4</ref> «e dimora in quella cità e
                  per lo reame»), while the V version (containing a slightly abridged text),
                  together with VB and R (who rework the text), omits this detail. On the other
                  hand, the erroneous variant of F (i.e. ‘pro’) could be interpreted as a
                  paleographic misunderstanding of the Franco-Italian preposition ‘por’ (&lt; PER),
                  widely used throughout the Parisian text (for instance, a few lines above, in <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 16</ref> we have «et s’en passe por
                     <placeName ref="#badascian">Badasian</placeName>et por une provence que
                  s’apelle <placeName ref="#pasciai">Pasciai</placeName> et por un’autre provence
                  ‹que› a a nom <placeName ref="#kesimur">Chesciemur</placeName>») . At the
                  beginning of the pericope, some redactions belonging to the α group contain the
                  variant «prises» Fr / «prexe» VA / «conquistato» VB (<ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c35_Fr2.35">Fr2 35 23</ref> «Et quant il ot toutes ces provinces
                  prises [Fr1 ‘princes’], il entra en <placeName ref="#ynde">Ynde</placeName>», <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 23</ref> «Quando el ave prexe tute
                  queste provinzie, el intrò in <placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>», <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TB40">TB 40 4</ref> «E quando egli ebe prese tutte
                  queste provincie, egli intrò in <placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>» and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22 18</ref> «e conquistato ch’ebe tute
                  dite provincie, entrò nel’<placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>»), which is to
                  be considered erroneous for three reasons: 1. the articulation of the ‘stemma
                  codicum’: <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35 17</ref> has «pisté» (error
                  for «passé», or ‘pounded, trodden, i.e. crossed by feet’), <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_V20">V 20 23</ref> «abiando passati»; 2. the lexical context in
                  which the word is placed, where «prises» could have been produced by «pristent» or
                  «prist», which follow immediately after(cf. F «pristent un noble cité», Fr «prist
                  la cité», etc.); 3. the overall meaning of the text: <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> does not conquer the three provinces of <placeName
                     ref="#badascian">Badakhshan</placeName>, <placeName ref="#pasciai"
                     >Pashai</placeName> and <placeName ref="#kesimur">Kashmir</placeName>; he
                  simply crosses them to reach <placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>. In the β
                  group, <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20 23</ref> is aligned with the
                  tradition («Et abiando passati questa provinzia che à nome <placeName
                     ref="#dilivar">Dilivra</placeName>, tolse quele zità de <placeName
                     ref="#diliDilivar">Delivra</placeName> et romaxe in quela; e tolse el reame de
                  uno che avea nome <persName ref="#asidinSoldam">Asendi soldan</persName>, el quale
                  era molto richo e possente; et chon quela zente romaxe in quel luogo et feva guera
                  a tute persone zirchostante al muodo ve ò dito di sopra, ché lui non temeva alguna
                  persona»), except for a little omission at the beginning of the pericope (maybe
                  due to a <hi rend="italic">saut du même au même</hi> on the term «provinzia»).
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 10-11</ref>, on the other hand,
                  offers a reworked version of the text («et finalmente entrò nella provincia di
                     <placeName ref="#melibar">Malabar</placeName> et prese per forza una città
                  detta <placeName ref="#diliDilivar">Dely</placeName>, et tolse molte altre città
                  circonstanti al detto <persName ref="#asidinSoldam">Asidin</persName>, perché li
                  sopravenne alla sprovista. Et qui cominciò a regnare»), perhaps derived from
                  source Z used by Ramusio. Unfortunately, the Toledan manuscript is incomplete here
                  (cf. <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 20-30</ref>), and this prevents us
                  from verifying the hypothesis. </note>
            </app>
            <app from="#c35_tr35_p12">
               <note>Our translation closely follows <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_F35">F 35
                     20-21</ref> («Or voç ai contés de ceste plaingne et de les gens que font fer la
                  scurité por rober. Et se voç di que messier <persName ref="#marcoPolo"
                     >March</persName> meesme fu {cel} come pris da celle gens en celle oscurité,
                  mes il escampé a un castiaus qui est apellés <placeName ref="#canosalmi"
                     >Canosalmi</placeName>; et de seç conpains furent pris aseç et furent vendus et
                  de tielz mors. Or voç conteronç avant des autres chouses»), whose text is
                  substantially confirmed by the whole tradition (α + β), except for the omission,
                  in almost all redactions, of the narrative transitions that are placed at the
                  beginning and at the end of the pericope («Or voç ai contés [...] por rober», «Or
                  voç conteronç [...] chouses»): likewise in <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_L29">L
                     29 9</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_R1.14">R I 14 14</ref>, <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c35_TA35">TA 35 12</ref>, <ref type="witlink"
                     target="#c34_V20">V 20 24</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c34_VB22">VB 22
                     21</ref>, <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Z14">Z 14 29-30</ref> and in the VA
                  family (where <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_P1.22">P I 22</ref> eliminates both
                  transitions, while <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_TB41">TB 41 1</ref> and <ref
                     type="witlink" target="#c34_VA22">VA 22 26-27</ref> only the closing one). As
                  often happens, Fr is the closest redaction to the Franco-Italian one; however it
                  is the only one to show a ‘singularis’ addition regarding the fairly small number
                  of <persName ref="#marcoPolo">Marco Polo</persName>’s companions who escaped from
                  the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ raid together with the Venetian: cf.
                     <ref type="witlink" target="#c35_Fr1.35">Fr1 35 26-27</ref> («Or vous ai conté
                  de ces males gens et de leur afaires, si vous [di] que mesires <persName
                     ref="#marcoPolo">Marc Pol</persName> meïsmes fu pris [de] cele gent en cele
                  oscurté; mais si comme Diex vout, il se bouta el chastel qui pres d’iluec estoit,
                  qui a a non <placeName ref="#canosalmi">Cahosabuy</placeName>, et perdi toute sa
                  compaignie, qu’i n’eschapa avec lui que .IIII. personnes. Or vous ai conté si
                  comme il avint, si yrons avant et vous conterons des autres choses»). Finally,
                  apropos of a peculiar variant of redaction V, where it is told that <persName
                     ref="#marcoPolo">Marco Polo</persName> was captured by the <term
                     ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term> «in ’sta pianura», instead of «en celle
                  oscurité» F, ‘oscurté’ Fr, etc. (<ref type="witlink" target="#c34_V20">V 20
                     24</ref> «Onde ve dicho che pocho manchò che non fosse prexo misier <persName
                     ref="#marcoPolo">Marcho Polo</persName> da questa zente in ’sta pianura»), see
                  the commentary by <ref type="bibl" target="#simion_2019">Simion 2019, 393</ref>.
               </note>
            </app>
         </listApp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
