<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="critical_translation_body" xml:lang="en">
         <div type="chapter" n="35" xml:id="c35_tr35">
            <head><hi rend="bold">#35</hi>
            <lb/>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p1" n="1">Here is described the city of <placeName
                     ref="#camandi">Qamadin</placeName></seg>
            </head>

            <p xml:id="c35_tr35_par1" n="1">
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p2" n="2">And after having gone downhill for those two days as
                  I told you, you find a large plain, <hi rend="italic">which extends(?) five days
                        <term ref="#midi">southhward</term>,</hi> and at the beginning of this plain
                  there is a city called <placeName ref="#camandi">Qamadin</placeName>, which was
                  once very big and very noble, but is now no longer so, because the <term
                     ref="#tartars">Tartars</term> from another country have ravaged it on several
                  occasions. And I tell you that it is very hot in the plain. And the province we
                  are now beginning to describe is called <placeName ref="#reobar"
                     >Reobar</placeName>. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p3" n="3"> Its fruits are <term ref="#dattal">dates</term> and
                     <term ref="#pomeParais">apples of paradise</term> and <term ref="#pistac"
                     >pistachios</term> and many other fruits that are not found in our cold
                  regions. And in this plain there is a species of bird called ‘<term
                     ref="#francolin">francolins</term>’, which are different from the francolins of
                  other countries: they are of mixed colour, black and white, and they have
                  red-coloured feet and beak. <seg rend="italic">It produces wheat and barley and
                     other cereals. On the slopes of the mountains that surround that plain there
                     are pomegranates, cedars and many other fruits and apples which do not grow in
                     our cold regions; countless turtledoves live there, on account of the many
                     berries they find there to eat; the turtledoves are really numerous, but the
                        <term ref="#saracinz">Saracens</term> never eat them, because they abhor
                     them. In those parts there are also <term ref="#faicain">pheasants</term> and
                        <term ref="#francolin">francolins</term> and many other birds.</seg></seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p4" n="4">The cattle are different too, and first of all I
                  shall tell you of the <term ref="#buef">oxen</term>. The <term ref="#buef"
                     >oxen</term> are very big and all white as snow; their hair is short and flat,
                  and this is due to the heat of the region; their horns are short and thick and not
                  pointed; between the shoulders they have a round hump two palms high: they are the
                  most beautiful thing in the world to look at. And when you want to load them, they
                  squat as <term ref="#giamiaus">camels</term> do; and when you load them, they
                  stand up and carry their loads very well, because they are very strong
                  indeed.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p5" n="5">There are also as big as donkeys, and their tails are
                  so thick and wide that they weigh thirty pounds <seg rend="italic">and even
                     more</seg>; they are very beautiful and fat and good to eat.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p6" n="6">In this plain there are many fortified cities and
                  towns that have high and thick earthen walls to defend the inhabitants from the
                     <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>, the marauders who carry out raids on
                  those lands. And why are they called <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>?
                  Because their mothers are <term ref="#yndien">Indians</term> and their fathers
                     <term ref="#tartars">Tartars</term>.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p7" n="7">And these marauders, when they want to carry out
                  raids across the country and pillage, are able to make the day dark with their
                  enchantments supported by the devil’s work, to the extent that, if one traveller
                  is not close to another, he can no longer see him; and they make this darkness
                  last for a good seven <term ref="#journee">days</term>.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p8" n="8">They know their territory very well. Once darkness
                  has been made to fall, they ride side by side, and sometimes they are ten thousand
                  men, sometimes more, sometimes less, and in this way they occupy the whole plain
                  in which they intend to carry out their raids, and nothing that they meet along
                  the plain can escape being plundered, whether it be men, cattle or goods/objects.
                  And once the <term ref="#caraunas">qara’unas</term> have captured men, they kill
                  all the old ones and take away the young and sell them as slaves.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p9" n="9">Their king is called <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName>. And this <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> went
                  to the court of <persName ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName>, who was a brother
                  of the <term ref="#grantKaan">Great Khan</term>, with fully ten thousand men of
                  his own people, and remained with him, because <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                     >Chaghadai</persName> was his uncle and a great sovereign; and while staying
                  with him, <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> conceived and implemented a
                  plan of great evil, and I shall tell you how.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p10" n="10">He left the court of his uncle <persName
                     ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName>, who was in <placeName
                     ref="#grandeArminie">Greater Armenia</placeName>, and ran away with ten
                  thousand of his men, who were very cruel and wicked, and crossed <placeName
                     ref="#badascian">Badakhshan</placeName> and a province called <placeName
                     ref="#pasciai">Pashai</placeName> and another one called <placeName
                     ref="#kesimur">Kashmir</placeName>, where he lost many of his men and beasts
                  because of the impenetrable and dangerous paths.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p11" n="11">And after passing through all these provinces,
                     <persName ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> and his men entered <placeName
                     ref="#ynde">India</placeName>, within the borders of a province called
                     <placeName ref="#dilivar">Dilivar</placeName>, and conquered a noble city
                  called <placeName ref="#diliDilivar">Dehli</placeName>. And <persName
                     ref="#nogodar">Nogodar</persName> took up residence in that city and in that
                  kingdom, which he had taken from a very rich and powerful king named <persName
                     ref="#asidinSoldan">Ghiyath al-Din</persName>. And <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName> lives there with his people, and he is not afraid of
                  anyone: he wages war against all the other <term ref="#tartars">Tartars</term> who
                  live in the lands surrounding his kingdom. <seg rend="italic">And in order to
                     know what this name ‘<term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’ means, I will
                     begin by telling you that a certain <persName ref="#nogodar"
                     >Nogodar</persName>, who was grandson of <persName ref="#ciagatai"
                        >Chaghadai</persName> (the brother of the <term ref="#grantKaan">Great
                        Khan</term>, who ruled <placeName ref="#grantTurquie">Greater
                        Turkey</placeName>), while staying at his uncle’s court, began plotting to
                     gain power: and therefore, having learned that in <placeName ref="#ynde"
                        >India</placeName> there was a province called <placeName ref="#melibar"
                        >Malabar</placeName>, not subject to dominion by the <term ref="#tartars"
                        >Tartars</term> and governed by a king called <persName ref="#asidinSoldan"
                        >Ghiyath al-Din</persName>, he took away about ten thousand men among those
                     he thought were the most ferocious and cruel, and with them he left his uncle
                        <persName ref="#ciagatai">Chaghadai</persName>’s court, without him
                     suspecting anything. He crossed <placeName ref="#badascian"
                        >Badakhshan</placeName> and then a province called <placeName ref="#kesimur"
                        >Kashmir</placeName>, where he lost many of his men and beasts because of
                     impenetrable and dangerous paths, and eventually entered the province of
                     <placeName ref="#melibar"
                        >Malabar</placeName> and conquered a city called <placeName ref="#diliDilivar">Dehli</placeName> by force, and wrested many other
                     surrounding cities from <persName ref="#asidinSoldan"
                        >Ghiyath al-Din</persName>, having caught him off guard. <persName ref="#nogodar"
                           >Nogodar</persName>
                     therefore began to reign in those lands, and the white <term ref="#tartars">Tartars</term> began to mix
                     with the dark-skinned Indian women, and these women conceived children who were
                     called ‘<term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>’, that is to say, in their language, ‘mixed’: and they are
                     precisely those marauders who carry out raids on the villages of <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName> and
                     also on other lands, as best they can. And as soon as they arrived in <placeName ref="#melibar"
                        >Malabar</placeName>
                     they learned the magical and diabolical arts, thanks to which they are able to
                     make darkness fall and to make the day dark, so that, if you are not close to
                     your companion, it is impossible for you to see him; and every time they want
                     to carry out raids they make such enchantments, so that people do not notice
                     them. And they ride for thirty or forty <term ref="#journee">days</term>, and mostly towards the land of
                     <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>, and this is the reason why: in winter, all the merchants who come to
                     trade in <placeName ref="#curmos">Hormuz</placeName>, if they have news of the arrival of merchants from <placeName ref="#ynde">India</placeName>, send
                     the <term ref="#mul">mules</term> and <term ref="#giamiaus">camels</term>, which have become lean from the long journey, to the
                     plain of <placeName ref="#reobar">Reobar</placeName>, where they can fatten thanks to the abundance of fodder: and
                     the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term>, who pay attention to these movements, go and plunder everything,
                     and capture men and sell them. However, if the prisoners can ransom themselves,
                     the <term ref="#caraunas">Qara’unas</term> let them go.</seg></seg>
               <seg xml:id="c35_tr35_p12" n="12">Now I have told you of this plain and the people
                  who make darkness fall in order to plunder. And I tell you that Messer <persName ref="#marcoPolo"
                     >Marco</persName>
                  himself risked being captured by those people in that darkness, but escaped to a
                  fortified city called <placeName ref="#canosalmi"
                     >Canosalmi</placeName>; and many of his companions were captured and
                  sold, and some of them were killed. Now we shall tell you of other things.
               </seg></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
